buddy welcome to children 4d today we'll
go over our tensorflow it's a good of an
experiment in the sense that I don't
think there's ever been a great like
deep learning class that already covers
tensorflow so we're now really at the
cutting edge of technology as such
there's no really other good material
you can learn from and we're doing this
experiment a little bit with you so
please feel free to ask questions during
this lecture I haven't been able to code
as much as I'd like to in the last
couple months so broth who's been
working with tensorflow extensively the
last couple of months that it's been out
only is going to give today's lecture in
terms of organization today the problem
set one is due so hopefully you're all
on time we have at most three late days
for this problem set if you have any
urgent questions who come to office
hours I can make some exceptions my
office hour today too if you're stuck
although ideally mine will be about the
project's thanks for all the ones who
have come already to project advice
office hour I'll try to also keep track
now and have a list so if you come let's
put down your name to make sure we
verify that you came to office hour for
the project well release problem set to
tomorrow it will be largely based on
tensorflow
once you know tends to flow very well
it's a very easy problem set but that's
a big if so hopefully today is useful I
think we went over this last night over
this lecture and if you pay attention
you could almost like copy and paste
things and it should always run you
should really be able to understand
every line code that we'll go over that
the Roth will go over so do do ask
questions when when they come up also
we've had around 40 people or so who
feel that the class survey thanks to
those 40 it looks like we improve the
amount so we're more like 55 to 60% of
people think it's the right speed right
now if that was a sample bias because
all the people who are happy or more
likely to take the survey and you're
unhappy please do fill it out
so we can adjust adjust to speed
accordingly because tensorflow is
non-trivial to set up and install we'll
have specialist sessions about
tensorflow
this week and then yeah you can always
of course ask in any office hour if you
have any questions we'll go especially
over how to set it up in AWS and now
they're very practically a useful skill
these days I can essentially start your
whole and cluster if you want and run
left many more experiments in parallel
that's that's about it are there any
questions about the organization problem
sets of stars No alright and take it
away
all right so I think let's we could
probably get started just by talking
about what's the state of deep learning
today so for those of you who've been
following kind of the deep learning
public library there's a kind of a zoo
of libraries out there there's like
Tiano Kyra's ku DNN MX net etc etc etc
and if you'll be if you've been
following attention each major company
basically has its own deep learning
library and many academic labs have
their own deep learning libraries so
before we even kind of dive into
tensorflow you need to start asking the
question which deep learning libraries
should we use and why should we bother
using it what are the kind of axes of
deep learning libraries and what are the
strengths and weaknesses that all the
different deep learning libraries bring
to the table so I think there's a few
axes you can use to kind of think about
deep learning libraries the first one
I'd say is when you are specifying a new
deep learning model are you writing a
config file or are you writing a program
so some of you may have experience would
say cafe or maybe some of you did an
internship at Google a couple years ago
and there's the disbelief system and in
these systems when you want to make a
new deep learning model you're not
writing code you're writing basically a
JSON file so you write down a JSON file
that specifies your complicated model
and once you specify this just on file
it auto creates the model for you
so in some sense this is convenient
because you're not you can think of a
deep learning model is kind of an object
that you specify statically and the nice
part is that if somebody else specifies
a deep learning model for you you can
copy/paste a config file you don't have
to write new code now the trade-off is
for anybody who's done a lot of things
which is on you know that things get
hairy quickly from complicated models
for things like recurrent neural nets
for very deep connell neural nets people
use in practice you get giant chess on
type files floating around so I think
there's a story in the cafe repo which
is one of the major deep learning
packages there is a 7,000 line
configuration file for the resident deep
network which is one of the imagenet
challenge winners for this last year and
the reason is that network has something
like 150 layers so they basically copied
the JSON config for one layer 150 times
so if you go into net you see 150
repeats of a config file so things get
hairy with config so as people built
experience with deep learning became
clear that you don't want to have config
file descriptions of deep learnings you
want to really have it be part of your
program you want to be able to use
standard programming constructs like for
loops or other programmatic constructs
to construct the complicated deep
networks people tend to use in practice
and I think in this problem set you'll
see a bit of that will make you
construct a recurrent neural net using
tensor phone you'll see how easy it is
it's basically ten lines of code in a
for loop when you do programmatically if
you're going to do it with the config
file that would be significantly more
challenging exercise and I think that
was a research paper at some point doing
it in cafe so let's assume now that
we're gonna stick with programmatic
construction of deep learning models the
next question is what language should we
use so if you've ever done a lot of
numerical computing you'll kind of know
that numerical programs have to be
written in kind of an optimized language
so for many years this was Fortran so
you'd have kind of mountains of Fortran
code sitting in the back end of all
these national labs running things like
nuclear nuclear simulations and the like
so today that's improved a little bit
you can actually use C++ to write
high-quality numerical code and there's
great libraries like eigen that'll make
this easy for you
but even so writing C++ is not in some
ways it's like writing a config file you
have to worry about a lot of things that
are not directly relevant to the
learning tasks at hand
things like memory management so in
practice most people tend not to write
C++ when they're making new deep
learning models or even numerical models
rather you want to have a high-level
kind of wrapper around the C++ that lets
you call into the C++ efficiently but
lets you use the syntax and the memory
management constructs of a high-level
programming language so there's really
two contenders into deep learning spaces
one is blue up and the other is Python
so ruins kind of the a game engine
wrapper it's designed to have very quick
Interop from C to law and the torch
library makes good use of Lua to write
scripts in it and basically tie directly
into the lower-level numerical code so a
lot of people really like torch some
people have some great stories with it
but the downside is torte mouaz not as
mature an ecosystem as Python
so pythons really were a lot of the
scientific community community the kind
of programming community the web
community resides nowadays and the
convenience of having all these
libraries at hand well something that we
felt we couldn't give up on so we
decided all right so let's use a
programmatic deep learning model let's
use one in Python and what are the
choices left
what languages what deep learning
packages will meet this criteria so for
those of you who know a little bit about
deep learning trivia there's you might
have heard of the package theano so the
OTO is kind of a symbolic tensor
manipulation package in Python in many
ways it's kind of the forerunner of
tensorflow and in some ways it's even
more advanced in tensorflow it's
certainly a more stable package it's
been around longer so you can ask why do
we use why aren't we using Tianna why
are we using tensorflow and part of it I
think it's a tensorflow
is new it's shiny that's one aspect the
other aspect is that tensorflow has kind
of more support for building giant
models so when you start building very
large deep learning systems one thing
you might want to do is not just you say
one GPU card to train your model but you
might want to what use a whole Bank of
GPU cards and if you start reading
papers in this literature you'll find
things like we trained on a bank of
sixteen GPUs for a week and you can't do
those types of experiments on a single
GPU so I think one place where
tensorflow really shines is the built-in
support for distributed systems so you
can kind of build distributed deep
learning models and we felt that that
was a skill that we wanted you to have
and that one's better served by having
you've learned tensorflow
but if you want to ever write models in
Theano you'll be able to use your
knowledge of tensor phone basically it's
almost a one-to-one mapping not quite
but you can you can port that knowledge
over so kind of for all these purposes
we decided all right let's go with
tensor flow and actually but we should
see a couple of caveats tensor flow is a
very new library so some of you might
try googling tensor flow versus Tiano
versus ax speed benchmarks and one
downside of tensor flow currently is
it's that it's actually
a reasonable it's a bit slower than most
of the other deep learning packages on
these benchmarks so you lose something
like 50% in speed on a single GPU today
but there's I know there's a lot of
smart and engineers at Google really
trying to hammer away at that so I think
that part will be fixed
so once assuming these things are fixed
that these are kind of we just want to
give you kind of a picture of the
landscape before we dive deep into
tensorflow and start talking about it so
now that we've kind of gone over a bag
of motivation the question is what is
tensor flow now the obvious answer is
you know it's a deep learning library it
lets you build deep learning models but
if it's a deep learning model a library
why didn't we call deep flow or
something why is it tensor flow and the
answer is at its heart tensor flow and
Theon or not really deep learning
libraries they're basically numerical
packages that make it easy to deal with
these mathematical constructs known as
tensors and the idea is it's a package
lets you define arbitrary functions on
tensors and lets you take their
derivatives easily now that of course
begs the question what is a tensor and
unless you have kind of makes extensive
background in numerical physics you
might not be that familiar with the
concept of tensor so I'll start by
saying the things that a tensor can be a
tensor can be a scalar a tensor can be a
vector and a tensor can be a matrix and
it turns out that when you if you fix
your math just right I have some details
on the slide and you can look this up or
you can go look in Wikipedia a tensor is
basically a multi-dimensional area of
numbers so for anybody of you who've
played with things like Python numpy
you'll know that there's very easy ways
to define say easy generalizations of
matrices kind of multi-dimensional areas
where you can say if you have a three
dimensional tensor you'd have three
index variables ijk so you can kind of
think about it as copies of a matrix
that you can index into so kind of the
goal that the reason that tensors are so
interesting useful for machine learning
is basically every operation you ever
and in any machine learning paper can be
written as functions on tensors and in
fact now this is a bit of a cute
exercise any operation basically in the
numerical chemistry numerical physics
any numerical literature that you can
find can be written as functions on
tensors so a neat little thing that
they've done in the tensor fodox you can
go look this up is they actually have a
partial differential equation solver
written in tensor flow which is really
cute it's the sort of thing that you
wouldn't expect a machine learning
library to be able to do but it's kind
of neat to know that it's there that
said it's a terrible PDE solver you
don't want actually use it for anything
but it's nice to know that you can it's
kind of reassuring so another kind of
analogy that I'd like to kind of come
back to is that a lot of people don't
compare deep learning libraries to kind
of standard numerical libraries but in
some ways that's really the comparison
we should be making tensorflow I'd I'd
argue is actually more similar to a
package like numpy in that both of them
are basically libraries built around
these n-dimensional
meat arrays and the idea is that these
multi-dimensional array manipulations
are at the heart of both packages so if
you know numpy I'm going to argue that
it's not that hard to actually figure
out tensor flow now the things that
tensorflow gives you that numpy doesn't
the biggest I'd say is that you can move
things on a GPU so there's a lot of code
are written in numpy and I've basically
been copy pasting it into tensor flow
with a few changes and I'm automatically
getting GPU usage and getting a 10x
speed up in my code which is a really
nice perk but of course the other big
one is that numpy doesn't really talk
about derivatives so if you define a
function on a numpy array you're
responsible for finding the derivative
of that function if you need to and
basically like we had to do in the last
homework you can find you can do some
matrix calculus and figure out those
derivatives but as an aside there are
Python packages that will automatically
differentiate functions on random numpy
arrays for you so in some ways tensor
floats I'd say GPU version of number
high with some extra intelligence baked
in for functions so let's kind of do a
very very quick recap of numpy
now I hope all this is familiar to
everybody here otherwise you're gonna
have trouble with homework that's due
today but the idea is let's numpy gives
us a bag of operations we can apply to
various matrices so in this case we're
doing something like we make a two by
two zero matrix one matrix and zero
matrix we sum it along an axis or we
might reshape it to have another shape
so these are kind of the standard array
matrix manipulation operations that
numpy allows you to do now the neat
thing is that you can basically do
exactly the same thing in tensor flow so
there's a lot of kind of things going on
in this slide so let me just kind of
kind of talk through what's going on so
in the last slide we said let's import
numpy as NP in this slide we say import
tensor flow is TF the next thing we will
do is we'll say there is a bit there are
a few bits of cabbage here that aren't
directly mapped at numpy and the little
arrows on the screen will tell you what
these bits of cabbage are for now you
can ignore them but kind of the heart is
we can call TF zeros to make a 2x2
matrix in tensorflow we can call reduce
sum which is the analog of the numpy
function sum to someone along an axis
and we can use get shape which is the
analog of shape in numpy and we can use
reshape which is the analog of reshape
itself so once you kind of have this
back and forth between numpy and tensor
flow in your head it's not at all hard
to start writing tensor flow you just do
the same things you do for a numpy and
you kind of carry it over and to help
you along this process we put together
like a small text sharing so a lot of
the operations you can do in numpy you
can basically carry over to tensor flow
tensor for one nice thing is it has
syntactic sugar so if you do things in
numpy like you have a matrix and you
multiply by a scalar and you add another
matrix there are these complicated
things called numpy broadcast rules that
make this all work out most of the time
and tensorflow
luckily has these same broadcast rules
baked in so you can't actually do things
like say five times a tensor flow tensor
will do what you think it should just
like it'll do what you think it should
in
so kind of has a bit of a confession
when I'm writing tensorflow
code I usually write in numpy version
then I translate each function one at a
time and for the homework this might be
something you might want to do try
writing something like the fordpass of
whatever deep network we ask you to
implement in numpy then just translate
it to tensorflow
if you know the function you're looking
for the tensorflow api you can it's
people on Stack Overflow don't have to
work you can say tensorflow version of
numpy some and there is in fact the
Stack Overflow post that'll tell you
exactly what this is so luckily the
large community that's built up has
already made these things but somewhat
digested so you can just use Stack
Overflow and Google to figure out these
tricks so now though we're gonna start
talking about the ways in which
tensorflow is not numpy and the first
one is that tensorflow requires explicit
evaluation what does that mean so when
you call NP dots arose and you make a
two by two array in numpy you can
display it directly it is basically what
you think it is when you dive down into
the sea it's a block of memory you've
allocated that has zeros filled out onto
it and it's basically a call to malloc
or something like that but if you look
at the tensor flow code that is not
what's going on when we call TF dot
zeroes and we try to print it out we get
this weird-looking tensor object so in
some ways the heart of tensorflow is
that although it looks like we're doing
direct operations on various
multi-dimensional areas there's actually
another hidden step so we'll return to
this concept kind of again and again
over the course of the rest of this
lecture but the idea is that tensor flow
is a system for defining operations on
these tensors and it forms a structure
known as a computation graph and the
idea is that you define a computation
graph and it's a symbolic entity but the
computation graph doesn't have any
values till you've run it in some
context so the key thing is that when we
call dot eval which you might remember
from all the slides previously we're
implicitly running the tensor flow
computation graph in a context and if
you remember that
bit about Kiev non-interactive session
that's a convenience that tensorflow
offers for you so it's setting up a
global environment so tensorflow
computations you can think of it as
creating these functions on these
multi-dimensional tensors then you're
setting up an environment for those
computations to exist then you execute
those computations in that given
environment so when we actually do up
here ta da eval we're saying use the
global environment execute the
computation specified by the tensor ta
in the context of this global
environment and in this case since ta is
just as zeros it does what we think it
should it makes a zeros array and it
kind of prints it out to screen so
that's kind of a critical bit between
tensorflow and numpy numpy is actually
doing operations on memory the minute
you tell to do anything tensorflow and
said you're describing operations that
you'd like to have happen then in some
sense they're compiled and you execute
those operations so there's kind of this
some symbolic barrier in between you can
get around it when you're playing with
things but it's very useful to keep in
mind that tensorflow is not numpy in
this one way so we were just talking
about kind of the need for executing
tensorflow in a particular context intel
in the tentacle library the object that
encapsulates this notion of an
environment is called a session so the
idea is that when you have a tensor flow
computation graph and when you define
some function on tensors you'd like to
have executed then you say I'm going to
start up a session then within the
course of this session I'm going to
execute this computation so in the
previous slides we use the function dot
eval tensor eval that's actually just
syntactic sugar a hundreth the hood what
dot eval says is find this session
that's currently in scope execute the
computation I asked in that session and
return me the result so the key bit at
the heart of tensor flow is basically
session dot run and there's a function
we're going to see again and again and
session don't run is basically how you
interface with the tensor flow
computation graph you have this abstract
computation you
this concrete environment the session
and you run the abstract computation in
the concrete environment to get a
numerical results then this is kind of
the workflow that goes on in tensor flow
and in this case we have a simple
example of doing something like that we
set up two constants we multiply the
constants and the key thing is that C 8
that is a times B is a symbolic value
until we create a session and run the
computation in that session when we run
that computation we get out 30 which is
what we'd expect but 30 does not happen
until we actually evaluate it here I'm
just yes yeah that's that's getting
gnarly so interactive session is just to
make life friendly for you in the shell
it's not what you should be using but if
you set up two different sessions and
you had a in the first session and B in
the second session that gets nasty I'm
actually not sure what would happen it's
it's the sort of thing that you
shouldn't be doing so you're welcome to
try like tenth flu is mostly polished
but every soften you'll do something and
you'll see this explosion of C++ errors
on to your screen and that's a sign
you're kind of taking the library in
directions that doesn't support yet but
it's a fun exercise I'd say try it out
there is in fact one thing I should
mention if you're going to start playing
with this well I'll talk a lot today
about computation graphs in tensor flow
now tensor flow in all the code that
will present in this class we're going
to have a global computation graph it's
going to be an entity that exists in the
ether but you can actually manipulate
multiple computation graph
simultaneously in tensor flow so you
could do things like you could set up a
in one graph B in another graph and then
they wouldn't be able to talk to each
other but again not this is sorry this
is a bit of an aside
tenser object without evaluating it into
another session
that isn't so the craft the graph exists
independent of session so computation
graph is an entity that exists so the
various tensors exist in the graph they
don't require the session to exist but
the particular numerical value set to
take on in one session need not have any
connection with the numerical values to
take on in the next session so that's
kind of the that's kind of the
connection there so here I'm just
repeating some things already said
interactive session is a useful tool and
another thing when you're debugging use
ipython use interactive session play
with tensors and print them out it's
very hard to gain intuition for these
things without actually running the
computations and interactive session is
your friend the other thing again oh
here's a bit of looking forward when we
say session dot run see we're actually
executing what in the tensor flow Docs
is called a fetch so fetch is basically
you have this abstract computation graph
and there's two operations kind of
jumping ahead you feed you put data into
the computation graph and you fetch you
take data out of the graph so you can
kind of think of the abstract
computation graph as creating a program
that you compile then maybe from the
command line you feed in some input args
to the program you've compiled and then
you take some on standard out so by
analogy to these shell programs the
input args are the feeds which we'll
talk about in a couple slides and the
output arcs are the fetches which will
again come back to in a couple minutes
Oh
so again just repeating things I
basically already said so computation
graphs are a central entity in
tensorflow computations every time you
call a function in tensorflow like when
we go back if you remember I said Kiev
dot constant or a times B you're
actually what that really translates to
you're saying is find the global conk
graph that is currently in scope add
these operations to that graph and hold
them within memory within that graph so
one kind of I'd say nasty thing about
tensorflow is that the
functions with respect to a global graph
that exists in the background so you're
not it's not quite functional in numpy
when you say a times B there is no
global memory that remembers that you
set a times B intensity flow there is
this global graph structure that's
recording every operation you make so if
you get weird things that go on you
might just want to sometimes close close
your session and restart it or like
control C it because there's this
implicit notion of memory that's handled
through the global graph and we've been
talking about this abstractly I put a
couple of pictures in following this so
hopefully that'll help you gain
intuition once you get to some more
complicated examples so we've talked
about some operations we've shown some
basic examples of numerical
manipulations you can do in tensor flow
and until now most of it's been
basically copy/paste from the pot but in
some sense tensor flow is more than just
an error a manipulation library you
could you could say it's basically a
prototypical programming language a very
simple one and any programming language
for that salt has variables so variables
in a standard program language are
basically boxes that hold state so
tensorflow similarly has the notion of
variables and when you're building a
machine learning model all the
parameters in that model you want to
hold in tensorflow variables so you can
think of say a weight vector in a
machine learning computation is
something that you want to put in a
white box and room go back and forth to
that box and put things in and take it
out and update it so really the notion
of having mutable variables is critical
for machine learning and so it's
critical for tensile and we have this
first class object the variable to
really help us get to it
so here we're gonna kind of walk through
a very simple use case of a variable so
a variable is a box and like it's
variable in a standard programming
language I very well does not have a
value until you initialize it so in C or
Python if you use a variable without
declaring it you're gonna get an error
or in Python or JavaScript I think you
can actually get away it'll be none or
something like that
basically that's a good way to think
about it a tensorflow variable is
basically
none it doesn't exist until we
initialize it in this case what we're
doing is we're setting up I think zeros
we're saying I'm gonna make a variable W
let's call it weights and this will
stand in for say a weight vector of the
type we might use in machine learning
language program and we're gonna
initialize this weight vector with the
zeroes matrix so one thing that you
kinda have to keep a note is that
tensorflow requires you to be explicit
about the notion of initialization so in
the former examples we've seen of
tensorflow we make a various constants
and we just run them in the in a session
and they come out correctly but you
can't do that for variables and the
reason in tensorflow logic is that
variables don't have meaning until you
initialize them so until you explicitly
initialize variables in tensorflow
and you do that with the call to Kiev
don't initialize all variables variables
will blow up on you and as you're
getting use of this you'll have a few
horrible error messages that say
something like onion initialize
variables cannot meaningfully be used or
something like that but the key thing to
remember the difference between a
constant tensor and a variable tensor is
a constant tensor doesn't have to be
initialized whereas a variable tensor
that is a box that holds value always
has to be initialized and you always
have to call initialize all variables or
it's more advanced cousins before
restarting computations on variables but
once you once you initialize them you
can do basically the same sorts of
things so you can use session don't run
and feed it in a variable and it'll
behave just like session don't run fed
in with the tensor and we actually have
a simple example of that on screen
nope I basically I set everything on the
slide there's kind of a dichotomy
between constant tensors and variable
tensors constant tensors feed in you'll
get to go variable tensors you need to
initialize something before we can start
doing things with that once you
initialize a variable it behaves
basically like a constant tensor but you
can do funkier things you can play
around with it and here's a nice example
of the sort of things you can do its
variables so if you remember back to our
on a programming 101 or whatever intro
to programming course you took one of
the first things you might implement in
a programming language is something like
the notion of a counter that is we have
some variable and let's say we set it to
serum and we're going to repeat an
operation some number of times and are
we good questions yes good question so
again it kind of comes back to this
notion of a computation graph so
remember when we do things in tensorflow
we're implicitly storing the
computations done in the global graph so
once we store something in the craft
there's a question of how do we get back
to it like maybe I created this graph
and another program elsewhere wants to
talk to that graph so you need some way
of indexing into the graph and the way
you index is by the name of the various
variables or nodes that are in the graph
so it's mostly convenient as a lookup
key there's things like there's things
like get variable which we'll talk about
later which allow you to query the graph
and get out a variable from this graph
so it's just a convenient way of
indexing is a global computation graph
yes why is the graph used that's a good
question I think the reason it comes
down to a graph is actually technical
we've covered the backpropagation
algorithm in lecture
over the last couple weeks and basically
it turns out that although we only made
you do back propagation to compute the
derivatives of these matrix multiplies
on the like it turns out that back
propagation is actually general and can
be extended to graphs so if you have I
think a directed acyclic graph you can
thinking back to algorithms class you
can linearize that into a chain and
going forward in the chain you can use
the back propagation algorithm to take
derivatives backwards through that graph
so in some sense kind of from a purely
purist perspective a graph is the most
general data structure on which you can
take the back propagation algorithm so
if you're doing it you might as well do
it on a graph because it's general the
other thing is it's useful in practice
recurrent neural nets or graphs kind of
complicated commercial networks or
graphs there are more complicated deep
learning algorithms like attention
models which you might say a bit about
that are even more complicated graphs so
basically you need you need the full
generality of graphs because there are
papers and useful deep networks or you
have graph structures and without that
generality you can't implement
everything you want to yes
so that's actually a very good question
um you need to handle it manually it
turns out it's very challenging to
actually distribute computations across
multiple compute units efficiently
so what tensorflow does under the hood
and we won't need this for the class is
that you can actually say put different
parts of the graph on different computer
substrates so you can say I want these
parts of the graph on GPU one I want
these parts on GPU two etc etc etc so
there are fine grained ways you can kind
of spread the graph out yourself over
various GPUs but there's no automaticall
way that'll do that's like one dream
people often have is well can I just
define him trillion by trillion matrix
and have it spread out into the ether
but no you can never do anything like
that all operations in the graphs must
fit within single GPUs but the nice
thing is you can put different parts of
the graph on different computer
substrates which is why this is a very
useful kind of answering your question
is well about why crafts it's a very
useful technique for handling word
computation is done in addition to
specifying complex computations
so the question is can you have
different variables of the same name tag
so it depends like we'll come back to
this again but there's a notion of scope
so you can set up namespaces and
tensorflow to have just as in Python you
can have say two function two variables
at the same name in different functions
that don't see each other you can do
something similar in tensorflow
you I think that a name does actually
uniquely specify a tensorflow variable
once you expand out all the scoping but
in the same scope two things that have
the same name do refer to the same
object so it does uniquely specify it
but you have scoping to allow you to
reuse names so you don't need to
constantly keep inventing new names yes
so the question is use the state and
counter so I'm not seeing a counter
variable which variable up there oh
sorry
I see all right this is this is actually
getting to a bit of so the question is
really there is there variable up there
is named counter in the string but it's
called state as a Python variable how do
these two things talk to each other and
this is actually getting to a good point
Python namespaces and tensorflow names
faces are different entities so counter
is an entity in in the tensorflow
computational graph whereas state is a
local variable in our Python script
these two things don't know about each
other counter doesn't know that in
Python we're talking about it as state
but even state you can reference in
check counter vise calling dot name
state dot name will give you back
counter so this is something that can
trip you up tensorflow namespaces and
tensorflow naming don't talk to python
namespaces and python naming so you can
think of it as pointers basically
there's something on memory
in the in the global graph and you have
kind of pointers that you can call
whatever but that doesn't change what's
in the graph unless you do it explicitly
or we do we have any more questions all
right
cool so let's return to talking about
this example so the idea of this example
hopefully you've had a chance to look at
it by now is there is a counter then
we're going to increment it and the idea
is we start by making a variable to hold
the counter and we call it counter in
Python we refer to it as a local
variable state and what we're doing is
we have two operations we have a TF dot
add operation and we have a T F dot
assign so one thing to note is that when
we make this new value that's calling
the tensorflow add operation on state
and on the constant one we are not
updating the original state we're just
making a new tensor in the graph that
happens to have the value of 1 plus
whatever is in the variable counter so
it's only when we call a sign to
explicitly overwrite what's held within
the counter variable that we update it
so you can look at the Python
translations on the right to give you a
rough sense for what's going on please
don't take this too literally like this
is this is at best a metaphor to help
you think about what's going on you
shouldn't read too much into the equals
plus 1 and all the things that are
written in the comments or on the right
so most of the time you won't actually
have to deal with the sign but if you
want to do complicated things where
you're updating variables or doing some
type of complicated machine learning
algorithm this is the type of thing
you'd want to do in practice various
optimizers that tensorflow has built-in
take care of doing these sorts of
updates for you so you usually don't
have to play with variables yourself
unless you want to
so we talked a bit about fetches and the
idea was that fetches are the way to get
informations out of information out of
the global computation graph and we've
typically been calling session dot run
on a 110 sir now you can just feed in a
list of lists of tensors and get the
values for all those tensors out so
nothing new here but the main reason I
want to emphasize this is if you read
the ten through flow dogs you'll see the
term fetch come up repeatedly
that's all fetch means you're calling
session don't run and you're feeding in
a list of tensors and you're gonna get
that list of tensors back from the
computation the more interesting concept
no actually before we go there I'll show
you the first picture what a computation
graph might look like so the first thing
I want to emphasize is this is this is
not what's actually going on in tensor
flow underneath underneath the hood this
is just a picture to help you think
about what's going on but if you look at
kind of that simple example we put up on
the previous slide we have three
constant tensors that we've defined and
the idea is that the first constant we
set it to three the second - - and the
third - five
then we take the second and third
constants we add them we get an
intermediate value and then we multiply
it by the first value to get out mole
and the notion of efetch is in the giant
black arrows that are at the bottom of
the screen those are the things were
pulling out of the computation graph
this computation graph has nothing going
in everything that's in there is already
specified within the text of the program
but we'll see examples of where we feed
in data and then we fetch it out but
this is a simple computation graph where
we're just fetching data from the
computation we're asking to execute so
any questions here does this notion of
computation and the graph begin to make
sense yes
we fetch in German and then maybe like
50 lines later after some others that
sweet bit efficient little device which
I was or the stuff in this project I'm
pretty sure it starts from scratch
unless you've updated the variable state
so if you've updated variable sate it
has memory if you don't it's functional
so this is a purely functional
computation graph no memory for people
who've done functional programming
you'll like this this is like you know
maps and reduces and all those good
things but unless you update method
variable state explicitly there is no
there is no change in the memory of the
system all right so now of course the
next question is we know how to fetch
data from a graph how do we put data
into the graph and there's a very simple
trick you can do you can you call
convert to tensor so if you have any
Python lists or you have a Python numpy
array you can just call convert to
tensor within within the tensor flow
computation that will directly pull it
in for you so when you're kind of
messing around in tensor flow in the
command line I suggest you do this just
use numpy to make some data so you know
what it is pull it into tensor phones
start playing with it so this is kind of
a good way to get start a good way to
start playing with things but it is a
little inconvenient if you want to do it
in a program so there is a more rich
built-in notion of how to feed in data
and the key concept is what's called a
placeholder variable so placeholder
variable is a special type of variable
but in some ways it's a dummy variable
in that you're not gonna update a
placeholder or you're not gonna do
anything with it except use it as a
receptacle for the user to put data in
that will be fed through the computation
graph and compute it upon so placeholder
variable is simply an input node in the
computation graph so the computation
graph we saw a couple slides back that
didn't have any input nodes because we
didn't have any input in there but we'll
shortly in a few slides come and see an
example of computations where you do
have placeholder nodes to feed in data
into the network
so here's a very simple idea of how you
might use a placeholder so we're going
to define two placeholders we're gonna
specify their types their floats so the
way you should think about it is input 1
and input 2 or 2 variables whose type
you've declared as a float and there's
nothing more known about them
so when we call output to be the
multiply to be input 1 times input to
output is a purely symbolic variable
because there is no numerical value
associated with it and this is where
it's useful to think about the
computation craft in the computation
graph it's a simple node perfectly well
defined but if you try to do this input
in numpy for example it's not clear how
you do that translation anymore because
there is not a notion of dummy
placeholder values in numpy so the idea
is that we make a concrete instantiation
in the session and we call session don't
run again but there's one new bit in
this and that's the feed debt which is
kind of over in the corner there so the
idea of a feed dictionary is that it's a
mapping from placeholder variables to
concrete numeric values in this case I
think we're setting 3 + 7 7 + 2 to the 2
inputs who are saying input 1 I want
that to be a 7 input 2 I wanted to be a
2 so you can kind of think about it as a
command line program where you have - -
input 1 7 - - input 2 - so each time you
run the program you can use a different
feed dictionary and that's analogous to
kind of calling the program with
different inputs so when you execute the
computation by calling it run and use
the fetch on output you get back the
value of output so you've used to feed
there to feed in value to the
computation graph use a session to
execute that computation and fetch the
value of output and you get out 14 now
this seems like an awful lot of trouble
but this is a very convenient it's a
very convenient metaphor to have and
will find it useful as we kind of go
further into the discussion so yes what
I would say say for example if you
declared them to have different shapes
that were incompatible at what stage
with since they give you an error does
it mean you try to run it or when you're
trying to just do oh well that's a good
question um I think it is when the
question is that if you have
incompatible states and you multiply
them
when does tensorflow give you an error
when it's defined or when it's run I
think it's when it's run I don't think
it has compiled kind of declarative
guarantees when you actually do it I
might be wrong about that though but I
think it's actually when you run in
it'll start blowing up on you and
tensorflow is finicky it does care about
these things numpy is kind of nicer
it'll massage things for you if it makes
sense tensorflow you actually have to
care about these things so I am actually
we're actually running low on time a bit
so I want to get to a big example so I'm
gonna hold off on quad taking questions
for a bit and try to get through to a
simple linear regression example that I
think will help you with the homework so
let's save questions for the end for the
next 20 minutes so here's a kind of one
improved version of the computation
graph we saw previously before we had
kind of a fetch we took data out of the
graph but there was nothing coming in in
this case we have a feed so that's kind
of the dictionary that's put up on top
that specifies the data flowing in so a
way to kind of read this graph is that
the part in the middle is a computation
you have this multiplication off you
have a feed coming in up top that pushes
data into the graph and you have a fetch
that pulls it out in bottom so very very
simple again for this it's not even
worth the trouble almost of drawing it
and when you start getting to more
complicated operations it helps to have
this abstraction and this way of kind of
thinking about these computations when
you're playing with us so before we kind
of go into a more complicated example
there's one concept which you kind of
touched upon in question earlier and
that's named spacing if you have
variables floating around in any
programming language you need some
notion of scope otherwise you're gonna
have like temp 1 temp 7 1039 floating
around so if you don't have some way of
controlling the Scopes of various
variables you're not gonna be able to
build complicated programs and in
tensorflow
the key things we
for that our variable scopes as a
variable scope is basically a simple way
of introducing a scoped environment into
tensorflow and get variable is a way of
retrieving a particular variable that
respects scope so this sounds terribly
abstracts we'll walk through a couple
examples to kind of see what's going on
so underneath the hood the name spacing
in tensorflow
is much like the names facing the file
system it's very simple so we have here
two nested scopes foo and we have bar
and when we nest is what you see is
we're basically just adding foo / as a
prefix to the name of the variable and
here we've called it V and it's in the
foo bar environment so we have foo slash
bar slash V and we have colon 0 to name
that it's to indicate that it's sum the
first variable named V excuse me in that
environment so for our purposes we're
not going to worry too much about the
colon 0 the part I think it's important
for you to count is the food slash bar
slash so you have scoped environments
and you have scoped names that let you
hold models now this won't be terribly
important for simple examples when you
start building complicated structures
complicated recurrent or convolutional
networks it does become important to
start thinking about namespaces because
otherwise you can't build the
complicated deep learning models so this
is a simple programming language
primitives that you should all be very
familiar with and it's a tensorflow
analog of that primitive there is one
other thing that names namespaces do so
one thing in deep learning models that
you often want to do is the notion of
what's called weight sharing so the idea
is that you have some ideas and belief
about how a model works and you might
say that in something like a recurrent
neural net there is some operation and
some transformation that exists at each
step in time and that's how we get from
the present to the future and this
transformation is the same at every time
step and this maybe agrees with our
notion of reality if there's some type
of description of reality there is the
same
underlying process happening at each
step now the way you represent that in a
machine learning model is used to do
something like wait time you say in a
recurrent neural net the weights that we
use at one time step key are the same as
the weights we use at P plus one and
cancer flow has a very convenient way of
viewing with this type of weight reuse
and the idea there is to use the
variable scope to control this so
there's a reuse variable in these
variable scopes and when you set by
default to reuse a set to false so when
you ask for get variable you're making
new variables each time it's creating a
new variable under the hood for you
whenever you said reused to false but
when you set reuse to true you can find
variables you've already created and in
something like a recurrent neural net
where you're going to reuse the same
weights at each time step this is
exactly what you want to have under the
hood so here's a simple case where we
have this scope foo
then we call get variable we make a new
variable there now we say reuse
variables and then we call get variable
again and we get back the exact same
variable we've called if you tried this
without that get scope it'll actually
blow up on you it'll say wait there's
two variables namely I don't know what
to do anymore
BAM and it'll crash but if you set this
then you are basically using weight
sharing and this is very convenient for
building complex models and you'll need
it on part of the homework so we do have
I think sometimes are there any
questions about variable scopes and how
they're used all right cool so I think
we've already talked a bit about what
kit variable does the key idea is that
depending on what's going on in the
global scope it does two different
things the first is that notice that get
variable respect scope implicitly if you
call get variable in scope foo it'll
look for food /v it won't look for bar
/v or any other scope so get variable
respect scope on Rita hood which makes
it sort of a convenience if we use a set
to false get variable creates new
variables for you under the hood
so it's kind of the preferred way of
making new variables deep inside a
tensor flow program but on the other
hand if you set reused true then what
get variables going to do is it's going
to search for a variable that exists in
the computation graph that you've just
created previously and when it doesn't
find it it'll blow up on it'll throw a
value error if it does find it you know
all is good we just find the same
variable again and here we basically
repeat an example much like the one we
showed and we we can kind of come into
and come out of variable scopes at
different parts of the computation so
it's a very nice way if you could say
encapsulating regions in the computation
graph and saying this part of the
computation graph is a conceptual hole
and I can enter and exit that part of
the computation graph so I still think
this is all pretty abstract so let's
jump into I think a simple example and I
think this will help tie all the
concepts we've talked about today
together so in many case in many ways
the simplest prototypical machine
learning algorithm is just linear
regression so you have some input
variable X and there's an output
variable Y and we want to learn a
mapping from X to Y and in this case
we've instantiate it a little bit of
sinusoidal ish data so we have a linear
ish increase in Y as x increases but
there's some type of sinusoidal noise
that's in the data so nothing fancy very
simple one-dimensional learning model so
how do we actually use tensorflow
to build a model on this data and how
are we going to put in all the pieces of
tensorflow mechanics we've learned to
actually construct something so this
slide has mostly cabbage but there's a
couple of concepts we've seen here that
I'll come back to first we need
placeholders if we're going to define a
computation intensive flow we need some
way of putting data into the Machine and
in a machine learning algorithm we have
input training data that we want to feed
into the computation graph so you're
gonna start by making X and white
placeholder variables that'll take in
the training data and the labeled
examples and use them to Train the
machine that we've defined and you see a
little bit in there about tensorflow
being finicky so
we do have to do some reshapes to make
sure the shapes match out nicely and I
think the best way to do this is just
write down what you think is reasonable
it'll blow up on you and just make
whatever small fixes it tells you to so
not that bad in practice but it is
something that hopefully they'll clean
up moving forward so now we kind of come
to the actual heart of the linear
regression algorithm so we have kind of
the model mathematically is we have some
rule some weights W we have some bias
beam and the rule the learnings of
linear function y equals W X plus P and
the idea is that conceptually W and B
all fit within kind of the same scope
there our linear regression module and
when we're having a deep network you
might have say the fully connected part
variable scope you might have the
convolutional variable scope the
recurrent variable scope in this case is
a very simple variable scope that is
just a linear regression variable scope
and we make two variables we make
weights and we make a bias and since
it's a very easy one-dimensional example
we say okay the shape is just 1 by 1 for
W and again 1 by just one for the bias
so these are both 1 dimensional
variables that we put in now we have the
two variables we have the placeholders x
and y for the input data which we define
in the free previous slide we have the
two weights W and V now what is it that
we're actually computing with and in
machine learning the central thing is
you know the loss function J so what is
a function that ties the variables in
the model to the data and here we define
the loss and the loss is simply going to
be the l2 loss we're gonna say Y minus W
X plus B let's take the sum of squares
over all the X and all the Y and that's
gonna be our loss function now how do we
define that in tensorflow
okay we have Y a vector of labels we
have X a vector of inputs and we have W
and B these constants so just do the
tensor arithmetic y minus W X plus P and
square it and now you have a tensor
sighs number of samples which is the
component wise error and then you do a
sum to get out the total loss function
and you can kind of piece together how
this relates to these symbolic
mathematics to reduce some is kind of
like the Sigma and kind of the written
out path and the Y minus W X plus B is
basically the Y minus y pred squared
part so are there any questions here yes
do we need to use the tensorflow ad
function to add B no because this is one
of the nice things tensorflow does some
limited broadcasting operations so it'll
figure out that okay W X is a tensor B
is a tensor do competent wise addition
of the tensor so you don't need to use a
dot add it syntactic sugar takes care of
it yes I think you can it's when you're
using a variable scope it's good
practice use get variable because you
might want to use weights again in
another part of the graph and use get
variable it'll respect these scopes and
it'll handle the underlying namespacing
if you wanted to do it yourself you
probably want to say something like
linear regression colon weights or
something and which gets nasty so this
is just a nice way to do and that you
should do in practice oh and I don't
know if I repeated the question the
question is do we need to use get
variable or do we need to or can we use
dot variable directly and the answer is
you can use it directly it's just mess
here yes sorry sorry I don't understand
the question the reused variable is the
same as copy numpy oh I see I see is it
the same as the copy matrix in numpy um
no so when we call numpy I'll copy we're
actually doing a memory copy there's a
region of memory that is in some matrix
and we're gonna copy it to another
region of memory when we do we use
variable we're saying are we going to
use the same node in the abstract
computation graph or are we gonna use a
new node in the abstract computational
graph so the key thing is remember
nothing happens in memory no computation
is executed until you create a concrete
session so this is all an abstract
construction and this is just a graph
that we're going to that we've defined
symbolically any questions
yes X&Y have to be yes basically because
you want to feed in user data to fit a
model you could make them whatever
variables you wanted to but if you want
to fit a learning model you do need
placeholder very you need you do need x
and y to be placeholder variables cool
all right
so in the form in the previous slide we
defined this variable los and the los
corresponds to the function J that we
use in machine learning practice now of
course as you're all familiar with it's
the key thing you want to do is del J
del W or del J del P that is we want to
be able to find the gradient of the loss
with respect to the parameters that
define the model in order to be able to
learn now how do we do this in tensor
flow so the nice thing is that tensor
flow implements a limited form of
automatic differentiation so for most
cases we don't actually need to minimize
losses ourselves we can instead use
tensor flows built-in suite of minimizer
objects or optimize our objects so the
idea is that an optimizer is just
another node in the abstract
computational graph and it's a special
node and it's one that if you pass in
some scalar tensor in this case los
it'll figure out what it has to do to
optimize that under the hood so if you
remember back to the assign variable
sorry the assign operation in the
counter example underneath the hood the
optimizer is doing something like an
assign operation it computes the
gradient of loss with respect to the
various variables in the network then it
uses a sign to do an update to those
variables and in this case we're using I
think the atom optimizer which is one of
the family of optimizers but for a
simple example you can think of this as
just a gradient descent step there's
some data olds you have some del datum
some update term which you've computed
and you're saying theta nu equals theta
old plus some fraction lambda times the
update del theta so it's the basic
gradient descent step
we've had you implement many times so
underneath the hood you can think of an
optimizers exit as performing this
update for us and it helps save us and
thinking questions so Adam is just a
convenient optimizer you don't need to
worry that's in some ways oh the
question is what is the Adam optimizer
and it is a particular type of optimizer
there are many advanced variants of
creating two-cent that are more or less
stable for different models I think the
reason I chose to use Adam here is I
think you'll use it in the homework and
the nice part about tensorflow is that
it encapsulate s-- a number of these
optimizers for you
so you don't necessarily even need to
know what adam is in order to use it as
long as you can make that API call that
said it's well written paper so I
recommend googling it and checking it
out or asking one of us at office hours
about it but it is a type of gradient
descent algorithm which is useful in
practice all right yes terms of is
partial support for automatic
differentiation Oh like do you know if
it will automatically differentiate the
whole sigmoid function one go or will
you compose it into you know the song
Division like how optimizes our
automatic that's actually the question
is how optimizes automatic
differentiation if you have something
like the sigmoid is it going to
decompose it internally or is it going
to do a more optimized thing to handle
it and the question the answer is it
really depends so I think for something
like sigmoid I think you can you can
implement it yourself Viking you can use
tensor flow dot X and various things and
in fact no we don't ask you to do that
in this one we ask you to implement
softmax in this homework with tensor
flow and we ask you to do it using
tensor flow primitives but for simple
things is a fine if you have a very
complex operation it might become slow
doing it the fully general way so I
think underneath the hood you can
actually replace some of these
operations and have kind of shortcuts
and the U but for this you need to write
new tensor flow code in the C++ API
under the hood so you can do it but it's
more like if you're a developer working
on tensor flow if you're a user you
should try to kind of stick with the
primitives because since it's much
easier it might be slower but it's
probably good for a first prototype that
or you can buy Bank of GPUs and just use
that and it's all ok all right any more
questions
so we should move on because this is
actually still pretty simple this is
just one gradient descent step that
we're showing here how do you actually
learn a model and this is where it
starts to get a little gnarly there's a
lot of things going on in this slide so
I'll just say a little bit about the
general idea without diving into details
when you're doing learning with gradient
descent the idea is that there's some
number of steps you're doing and in each
step you're taking a fraction of the
input data and upon that fraction the
input data you're computing the
derivative of the loss function on that
input data with respect to the
parameters that came in and based on
those derivatives you're going to do an
update to the variables that you're
stored and this tensor flow code
basically does exactly this for you it's
saying that there
some number of steps 500 which we're
gonna take at each step we're gonna take
our input numpy arrays and by the way
this one the really nice things about
programmatic design deep learning api's
is you can do things like I'm just gonna
randomly sample my numpy matrix using
random choice whereas if you're gonna do
it in a proto proto-language you have to
do horrible things like write down
random files on disk where you've
pre-show fell'd and then written down a
shuffled version on disk or as here it's
so much nicer you use numpy to do random
sub-samples for you and you can do
things on the fly so we take a random
sub sample I think our batch size here
is whatever our batch sizes and then we
say alright let's just use the optimizer
that we defined in the previous step to
take one gradient descent step on this
mini batch so this is kind of composing
all the various operations so this is
kind of abstract so it might be nicer to
kind of look at it visually what is
actually going on so this is a
complicated diagram so let's kind of
break it into parts so if you remember
sort of the visual language that we've
set up fetches or the black fat arrows
there are things that come out of graph
the orange things coming in up top are
the feeds it's already put data into the
graph so the idea of this graph is that
we're computing this cost function which
we put up on the screen and we feed in
some datum that is the mini batch of
data that we're putting in we pulse it
through the graph and we fetch out and
we fetch out the optimizer and the idea
is that one fetch of data from the graph
given a feed of the mini batch is going
to execute a single step of gradient
descent so the for loop that we saw in
the previous slide is basically you
could say I kind of like to think about
as a wave almost like you're putting in
data it's like pulsing forward through
the graph and you fetch it out and your
repeating is like data motion 500 times
in the computation and that's what
tensor flow is it's a system for
defining computational graphs to compute
functions and in this case the function
we
computing which might be easier to read
from the math is just as l/2 losting we
defined this function as a graph we put
in data and we pulse it through the
graph and we pull out the loss and we
use a special optimizer to update the
internal state and we do this 500 times
in a for loop and this is kind of the
heart of what is going on in tensor flow
so I think here I'm going to pause and
take questions because I this is the
critical bit of what's going on in 10
suppose so floor open yes
so why is there a underscore just like
you don't care about ah so the
underscore the question is why is there
an underscore and that's just a pythonic
style if there's a variable that for
some reason you need to have returned to
you but you don't really care what the
value is you use an underscore in this
case that's the optimizer operation so
we want to fetch the optimizer operation
from the graph but in some sense we
don't care what it returns we just
wanted to do the update to the internal
state so this is actually a way of just
writing documenting in our program we
don't really care what's the output of
the optimizer operation we just wanted
to update an internal state but then yes
so an operation in this case one the
optimizers for example there's a
gradient descent optimizer an atom
optimizer those are operations so we
didn't really go into what a tensorflow
operation is but they're just you can
think of as parts of the computation
graph that do things like update
internal state but they're just parts of
the computation graph like everything
else and I think in fact addition or
multiplication is an operation they
don't even have to update its as some
transformation of tensors that's
computed internally within the graph and
the question was what is an operation
and do we have to know much about it no
not really it's just a part of the Kraft
yes
parallel and just updating herdsman yeah
that's a good question so the question
is is there a way to make this four loop
run in parallel and just have tensorflow
take care of that underneath the hood
for us I think the way you do this is
basically that's a good question
you could there is a way to do this
there is a way to set it up and do it
distributed creating descent workers and
I think I'm little fuzzy on this but I
think you define a function and there's
some type of broadcast you say that
you're gonna do it on a variety of GPUs
I don't know I haven't looked into this
carefully and it just came out in the
supported API so I'm gonna punt on this
but yes so the question is why do random
choice in gradient descent usually
random choice is actually helpful for
maintaining stability of a learning
model and when this becomes really
useful is if you have something if
different parts of the data are
qualitatively different from other parts
of the data and you have a large enough
data set models exhibit what's known as
forgetting so like if you start saying
with the data from two years ago
and you work your way up to sequentially
to the data from yesterday the
distribution of data from two years ago
might be really different from
distribution today so there's a lot of
forgetting that could happen you could
forget the patterns that came in the
past because you're learning the
patterns in the present but if you do
kind of this jumbled shuffle you have to
account for all the data you have to
account for a random sample the data
which means the model can't forget so in
practice it's healthier to do a random
sub choice when doing an update to the
model use that ensures you've got
everything in there
questions are we good yes so the
question is a random choice versus a
random shuffle ah I see I see I see okay
so why not just randomly shuffle the
data once and not worry about it yes
absolutely you can do that there is no
difference in practice this is just
convenient and I was hacking together
Python scripts I was like why not if you
have a large enough data set you might
not want to do this choice in real time
use that will get you cash problems
you're right so it is for large data
sets it's probably smarter to do a
shuffle before time and write it down
yes
so the question is is there practical
suggestion for what a batch size should
be and the answer I found is something
like small powers of 2 32 64 128 there
is really it's in some sense it's a
hyper parameter it's some aspect of the
model training that really depends on
your hardware on your particular data
set you just I'd say try out a few on
your validation set see what works
better most of the time it doesn't make
a big difference like yeah batch size
one probably don't want that batch size
50,000 and probably don't want that but
anything in kind of the smaller regime
it's mostly it's mostly all the same you
can try out a few things it's basically
hyper parameter try it out empirically
there's no real good rule of thumb all
right we do have a few more slides so
I'm gonna break your if there are no
more questions okay so here again we
have this complicated graph thing and it
fits a nice model so you can see if the
straight line so machine learning works
tensorflow is great we're done we're out
of a job you know this you can write
tiny scripts so basically this is kind
of a toy learning example in tensorflow
but all the programs that you'll write
for doing non-trivial learning in
tensorflow will have very much the same
structure you'll have these for loops
you'll perform you'll define this
computation graph that is your model up
front you'll take in your data in
placeholders you'll add eat yoga for
loop in which it takes some fraction
that data then you'll run the graph one
time that is the model that will update
the parameters in that model and you'll
repeat until you feel you're done and
what done is depends there's many in
practice you should be doing something
like tracking error on a validation set
because this was a tiny toy example we
didn't do that but in practice you
should not be doing what I'm doing on
the screen you should be doing something
healthier and the homework does make you
actually look at error on a validation
set but for now this is okay so the one
thing we really didn't talk too much
about today is that how does this
automatic differentiation happen on
the hood and I think we touched upon a
little bit in a question in that it's
just a back propagation algorithm that
you've already learned a bit about and
the idea is that when people were
defining tensorflow as they define
things like addition multiplication or
exponentiation for each operation each
primitive they wrote down a gradient
function associated with it so each
tensorflow primitive underneath the hood
has had somebody write down a pair of
gradient function so if you have
exponential you have a gradient of
exponential function if you have
addition you have a gradient of addition
function and the idea is that when you
build up a graph with these primitive
nodes you when you're doing the forward
pass you use the function addition
multiplication exponentiation when
you're doing the backward pass as in
back propagation you use the paired
gradient function and you use that just
to use the calculus chain rule and
propagate information through the graph
so there's nothing that magical in fact
it's not that hard homework exercise to
just do this and write like a mini
automatic differentiation and for I I
I'm actually the one writing the song
yourselves thinking of XI we're having
something like that in there but I
decided not to but it's not that bad
it's something you could do and it's
something that you shouldn't think about
ten circles magic it's just doing some
simple math underneath the hood but it's
nicely implemented so you don't have to
worry about it
so practical suggestions I think we've
touched on many of these already I think
the key thing is that when you're
getting used to tensor flow it helps to
think about it as sort of a numpy
wrapper try doing things like writing
functions and numpy convert the numpy
areas to tensors print things out things
that will trip you up tensor flow is
fastidious about things like shapes and
types so you will get things like in 32
given where float 32 is expected simple
things like that just it's not serious
just figure out what tensorflow is
asking for what it's expecting and it'll
work out one thing that won't trip you
up is that some operations that are very
natural in numpy are not directly
supported in tensor flow so numpy you
can do nice things like index into it
multi-dimensional area with another
multi-dimensional array and if you're
going to implement softmax in the vector
eyes
version in numpy there's a very natural
way to do this and some of you might
have even used it in the last term work
that natural implementation will
actually work out in tensor flow there's
like open github issues and people
complaining so I think they'll fix it
but you'll have to be smart so a lot of
beginning with tensor flow is about
knowing how to start from the numpy
version and then distort it to work
within the tensor flow API and we'll
give you some exercises that'll make you
work through this process and kind of
internalize it
the other thing again is interactive
interactive session is your friend use
ipython debug things the tensor flow API
is a little dense at time so it helps to
know what you're looking for so try
writing a version in numpy do a
translation one at a time use tools
other people have already built to help
you just look at it and Stack Overflow
or something so kind of doing the
translation is easier than trying to
write it from scratch another thing
which we didn't touch on in this lecture
tall is tensor board so one of the
really nice things about tensor flow is
it gives you kind of a visualization
toolkit to look at models you've created
and to look at the learning process as
it's happening now we're not going to
use that much in the class the main
reason is that tensor board is kind of
built to run on your localhost if you
want to use it running on a remote
server you need to do things like SSH
port forwarding which gets a little
hairy and we didn't really want to make
you deal with it it's a nice tool if
you're gonna do your projects you might
look at it if you're having trouble but
you don't need to do it for anything
that you'll use in this class but we
encourage you to play with it on your
own time so kind of the most important
question the last minute is work can you
use tensor flow at Stanford and the
answer I think for most of you is just
go on corn it's up on corn now so you
should be able to log in to corn load up
the tensor flow module and run the
computation and for the homework we
don't need you to use a GPU you should
be able to run all the homework on the
CPU corn implementation if you do have
access to a Stanford GPU clustered
something like Sherlock or Xtreme
feel free to use it like it'll make life
faster but
the homework should he's made to be
runnable on a cpu implementation and you
should be fine
if you want to do things like experiment
with with AWS and GPUs will have a
special we'll have a special session
Xiao Jing one of the keys is going to
host the session discussing telling you
how to get up on a table yes and we have
a machine image that will make it easier
to easy for you start running tensorflow
so go to his session on Sunday and as a
final thing here is a little hint for
the homework so in the homework you'll
have to define embedding matrices and
these are some it's your just some
functions that you might find useful so
just take a look at the slides if you're
stuck on the homework and with that I
think we're done are there any last
questions yes that's a good question
easiest way just remove it from the
graph I think there is a way to set a
variable to be non learned I'm not sure
about the API version but I think you
can do this in practice ifs employees
just comment out that part of the code
but the question is how do you ask
certain parts of the computation graph
not to be optimized and I am reasonably
certain there's a way to do this but I
don't know off the top of my head
question
honey does tension to handle the pointy
bits good question so if you have a
non-differentiable loss function like ER
lu does tensorflow handle it and yes it
does underneath the hood it handles it
by ignoring it it turns out that you
almost never hit the point of it so you
can just pretend it's all hunky-dory and
it works out basically all the time and
on the pointy bits you just pick one of
the sides to kind of pick your
derivative and it the convergence proves
like for those of you are interested
Steve Boyd's class talks about this in
convex optimization there's like sub
gradient convergence theorem so things
all work out on the pointy bits in
practice you just pretend it's out there
and it's fine all right cool well thank
you for listening everybody